I've been following in my mother's footsteps since before I was even born and haven't figured out how to stop. And as I get older, it does get harder. No seriously, it gets harder. (Laughter) My mother's taught me many things, though, most of all that love overrules. She's taught me that love is an action, not a feeling. Love is a way of being, it's a way of doing, it's a way of listening and it's a way of seeing. DW: And also, the idea about love, photographers, they're looking for love when they make photographs. They're looking and looking and finding love. Growing up in North Philadelphia, I was surrounded by people in my family and friends who made photographs and used the family camera as a way of telling a story about life, about life of joy, about what it meant to become a family in North Philadelphia. So I spent most of my life searching for pictures that reflect on ideas about black love, black joy and about family life. So it's really important to think about the action of love overrules as a verb. HWT: Sometimes I wonder if the love of looking is genetic, because, like my mother, I've loved photographs since before I can even remember. I think sometimes that -- after my mother and her mother -- that photography and photographs were my first love. No offense to my father, but that's what you get for calling me a "ham" wherever you go. I remember whenever I'd go to my grandmother's house, she would hide all the photo albums because she was afraid of me asking, "Well, who is that in that picture?" and "Who are they to you and who are they to me, and how old were you when that picture was taken? How old was I when that picture was taken? And why were they in black and white? Was the world in black and white before I was born?" DW: Well, that's interesting, just to think about the world in black and white. I grew up in a beauty shop in North Philadelphia, my mom's beauty shop, looking at "Ebony Magazine," found images that told stories that were often not in the daily news, but in the family album. I wanted the family album to be energetic for me, a way of telling stories, and one day I happened upon a book in the Philadelphia Public Library called "The Sweet Flypaper of Life" by Roy DeCarava and Langston Hughes. I think what attracted me as a seven-year-old, the title, flypaper and sweet, but to think about that as a seven-year-old, I looked at the beautiful images that Roy DeCarava made and then looked at ways that I could tell a story about life. And looking for me is the act that basically changed my life. HWT: My friend Chris Johnson told me that every photographer, every artist, is essentially trying to answer one question, and I think your question might have been, "Why doesn't the rest of the world see how beautiful we are, and what can I do to help them see our community the way I do?" DW: While studying in art school -- it's probably true -- I had a male professor who told me that I was taking up a good man's space. He tried to stifle my dream of becoming a photographer. He attempted to shame me in a class full of male photographers. He told me I was out of place and out of order as a woman, and he went on to say that all you could and would do was to have a baby when a good man could have had your seat in this class. I was shocked into silence into that experience. But I had my camera, and I was determined to prove to him that I was worthy for a seat in that class. But in retrospect, I asked myself: "Why did I need to prove it to him?" You know, I had my camera, and I knew I needed to prove to myself that I would make a difference in photography. I love photography, and no one is going to stop me from making images. HWT: But that's when I came in. DW: Yeah, that year I graduated, I got pregnant. Yep, he was right. And I had you, and I shook off that sexist language that he used against me and picked up my camera and made photographs daily, and made photographs of my pregnant belly as I prepared for graduate school. But I thought about also that black photographers were missing from the history books of photography, and I was looking for ways to tell a story. And I ran across Gordon Parks' book "A Choice of Weapons," which was his autobiography. I began photographing and making images, and I tucked away that contact sheet that I made of my pregnant belly, and then you inspired me to create a new piece, a piece that said, "A woman taking a place from a good man," "You took the space from a good man," and then I used that language and reversed it and said, "I made a space for a good man, you." (Applause) HWT: Thanks, ma. Like mother, like son. I grew up in a house full of photographs. They were everywhere, and my mother would turn the kitchen into a darkroom. And there weren't just pictures that she took and pictures of family members. But there were pictures on the wall of and by people that we didn't know, men and women that we didn't know. Thanks, ma. (Laughter) I have my own timing. Did you see her poke me? (Laughter) Puppet strings.
He estado siguiendo los pasos de mi madre desde antes de nacer y no he descubierto cómo detenerlos. Y a medida que envejezco, se vuelve más difícil. No, en serio, cada vez es más difícil. (Risas) Mi madre me enseñó muchas cosas sobre todo, que el amor manda sobre todo. Ella me enseñó ese amor es una acción, no es un sentimiento El amor es una forma de ser, es una forma de hacer, es una forma de escuchar y es una forma de ver. DW: Y también, sobre la idea del amor, los fotógrafos, buscan amor cuando hacen fotografías. Miran y miran y encuentran el amor. Criado en el norte de Filadelfia, Estaba rodeado de personas de mi familia y amigos quienes hicieron ls fotografías y usaron la cámara familiar como forma de contar una historia sobre la vida, sobre la vida de alegría, sobre lo que significaba convertirse en una familia en el norte de Filadelfia. Así que pasé la mayor parte de mi vida buscando imágenes que reflejan ideas sobre el amor negro, la alegría negra y sobre la vida familiar. Es importante pensar en la acción del amor por encima de las reglas como un verbo. HWT: A veces me pregunto si el amor de mirar es genético, porque, como a mi madre, me encantan las fotografías desde antes incluso de recordar. A veces pienso que, después de mi madre y su madre, la fotografía y las fotografías fueron mi primer amor. Sin ofender a mi padre, pero eso es lo que se obtiene de llamarme "jamón" donde quiera que vayas. Recuerdo que cada vez que iba a la casa de mi abuela, ella escondeía todos los álbumes de fotos porque tenía miedo de que preguntara, "¿Quién es ese en esa foto?" y "¿Quiénes son para ti y quiénes son para mí? y ¿qué edad tenías cuando se tomó esa foto? ¿Qué edad tenía yo cuando se tomó esa foto? ¿Y por qué eran en blanco y negro? ¿Era el mundo en blanco y negro antes de que yo naciera? DW: Es interesante, al pensar en el mundo en blanco y negro. Crecí en un salón de belleza en el norte de Filadelfia, el salón de belleza de mi madre, mirando "Ebony Magazine" viendo fotos que contaban historias que a menudo no aparecían en las noticias, pero en el álbum familiar Quería que el álbum familiar fuera enérgico para mí, una forma de contar historias, y un día me encontré con un libro en la Biblioteca Pública de Filadelfia llamado "The Sweet Flypaper of Life" de Roy DeCarava y Langston Hughes. Creo que amis 7 años lo que me atrajo fue el título, el papel matamoscas y lo dulce, pero a los siete años, miraba las bellas imágenes que hizo Roy DeCarava y luego busqué la forma de contar una historia sobre la vida. Y buscarme es el acto que básicamente cambió mi vida. HWT: Mi amigo Chris Johnson me dijo que cada fotógrafo, cada artista, esencialmente trata de responder una pregunta, y creo que tu pregunta podría haber sido, "¿Por qué el resto del mundo no ve lo hermosos que somos, y ¿qué puedo hacer para ayudarlos a ver a nuestra comunidad como yo?" DW: Cuando estudiaba en la escuela de arte, probable sea cierto, tuve un profesor que me dijo que ocupaba el espacio de un buen hombre Trató de reprimir mi sueño de convertirse en fotógrafa. Intentó avergonzarme en una clase llena de fotógrafos varones. Me dijo que estaba fuera de lugar y fuera de orden como mujer, y él continuó diciendo que todo lo que podía y debería hacer es tener un bebé y dejar a un buen hombre su asiento en esa clase. Me sorprendió el silencio en esa experiencia. Pero tenía mi cámara, y estaba decidido a demostrarle que era digna de un asiento en esa clase. Pero en retrospectiva, me pregunté: "¿Por qué tengo que demostrarlo?" Tenía mi cámara, y sabía que debía probarme a mí mismo que marcaría una diferencia en la fotografía. Me encanta la fotografía, y nadie me impediría hacer fotos. HWT: Entonces fue cuando llegué yo. DW: Sí, ese año me gradué y me quedé embarazada. Sí, él tenía razón. Y te tuve a ti, y me quité ese lenguaje sexista que él usó en mi contra y recogí mi cámara e hice fotografías diariamente, e hice fotos de mi barriga embarazada mientras me preparaba para la escuela de postgrado. Pero también pensé que faltaban fotógrafos negros en los libros de historia de la fotografía, y estaba buscando formas de contar una historia. Y encontré el libro de Gordon Parks "Una elección de armas" que era su autobiografía. Empecé a fotografiar y hacer imágenes, y escondí esa hoja de contacto que hice de mi vientre embarazado, y luego me inspiraste a crear una nueva pieza, una pieza que decía: "Una mujer tomando el lugar de un hombre bueno" "Tomaste el espacio de un buen hombre" y luego usé ese lenguaje y lo invertí y dije: "Hice un espacio para un buen hombre, tú". (Aplausos) HWT: Gracias, ma. Igual que la madre, el hijo. Crecí en una casa llena de fotografías. Estaban en todas partes, y mi madre convertía la cocina en un cuarto oscuro. Y no solo había fotos que ella tomaba y fotos de miembros de la familia. Había fotos en la pared de y por personas que no conocíamos, hombres y mujeres que no conocíamos. Gracias, ma. (Risa) Tengo mi propio tiempo. ¿Vieron como me empujaba? (Risas) Cuerdas de marionetas.
I grew up in a house full of photographs. (Applause) But they weren't just pictures of men and women that we knew, but pictures of people that I didn't know, Pretty much, it was pretty clear from what I learned in school, that the rest of the world didn't either. And it took me a long time to figure out what she was up to, but after a while, I figured it out. When I was nine years old, she published this book, "Black Photographers, 1840-1940: A Bio-Bibliography." And it's astounding to me to consider that in 1840, African Americans were making photographs. What does it mean for us to think that at a time that was two, three decades before the end of slavery, that people were learning how to read, they had to learn how to do math, they had to be on the cutting edge of science and technology, to do math, physics and chemistry just to make a single photograph. And what compelled them to do that if not love? Well, that book led her to her next book, "Black Photographers, 1940-1988," and that book led to another book, and another book, and another book,
Crecí en una casa llena de fotografías. (Aplausos) Pero no eran solo imágenes de hombres y mujeres que conocía, sino con fotos de personas que no conocía, y era bastante obvio que por lo que aprendí en la escuela, el resto del mundo tampoco los conocía. Y me llevó mucho tiempo descubrir qué estaba tramando, pero después de un tiempo, lo descubrí. Cuando tenía nueve años, ella publicó este libro, "Black Photographers, 1840-1940: Una bio-bibliografía". Y me asombra ver que en 1840 los afroamericanos hacían fotografías. ¿Qué supone pensar en ello en una época que sucedió dos o tres décadas antes del final de la esclavitud, cuando estas personas estaban aprendiendo a leer, tenían que aprender matemáticas, tenían que estar a la vanguardia de la ciencia y la tecnología, hacer matemáticas, física y química solo para hacer una sola fotografía? ¿Y qué los impulsó a hacer eso sino al amor? Ese libro la llevó a su siguiente libro, "Black Photographers, 1940-1988". y ese libro llevó a otro libro, y otro libro, y otro libro,
and another book, and another book,
y otro libro, y otro libro,
and another book, and another book, and another book, and another book, and another book, and another book, and another.
y otro libro, y otro libro, y otro libro, y otro libro, y otro libro, y otro libro, y otro.
(Applause) And throughout my life, she's edited and published dozens of books and curated numerous exhibitions on every continent, not all about black photographers but all inspired by the curiosity of a little black girl from North Philadelphia. DW: What I found is that black photographers had stories to tell, and we needed to listen. And then I found and I discovered black photographers like Augustus Washington, who made these beautiful daguerreotypes of the McGill family in the early 1840s and '50s.
(Aplausos) Y a lo largo de mi vida, ella ha editado y publicado docenas de libros y comisariado numerosas exposiciones en todos los continentes, no todo sobre fotógrafos negros, sino todo inspirado en la curiosidad de una niña negra del norte de Filadelfia. DW: Lo que encontré es que los fotógrafos negros tenían historias que contar, y necesitábamos escuchar. Y luego encontré y descubrí fotógrafos negros como Augustus Washington, quien hizo estos hermosos daguerrotipos de la familia McGill a principios de los años 1840 y 50.
Their stories tended to be different, black photographers, and they had a different narrative about black life during slavery, but it was also about family life, beauty and telling stories about community. I didn't know how to link the stories, but I knew that teachers needed to know this story. HWT: So I think I was my mother's first student. Unwillingly and unwittingly -- puppet strings -- I decided to pick up a camera, and thought that I should make my own pictures about the then and now and the now and then. I thought about how I could use photography to talk about how what's going on outside of the frame of the camera can affect what we see inside.
Las historias de fotógrafos negros tendían a ser diferentes, y tenían una narrativa diferente sobre la vida negra durante la esclavitud, pero también trataban de la vida familiar, la belleza y contar historias en la comunidad. No sabía cómo vincular las historias, pero sabían que los maestros debían saber esta historia. HWT: Creo que fui el primer estudiante de mi madre. Involuntariamente e involuntariamente, cuerdas de marionetas. Decidí tomar una cámara, y pensé que debería hacer mis propias fotos sobre el entonces y ahora y el ahora y el entonces. Pensé en cómo podría usar la fotografía para hablar sobre lo que sucede fuera del marco de la cámara puede afectar lo que vemos dentro.
The truth is always in the hands of the actual image maker and it's up to us to really consider what's being cut out. I thought I could use her research as a jumping-off point of things that I was seeing in society and I wanted to start to think about how I could use historical images to talk about the past being present and think about ways that we can speak to the perennial struggle for human rights and equal rights through my appropriation of photographs in the form of sculpture, video, installation and paintings. But through it all, one piece has affected me the most. It continues to nourish me. It's based off of this photograph by Ernest Withers, who took this picture in 1968 at the Memphis Sanitation Workers March of men and women standing collectively to affirm their humanity. They were holding signs that said "I am a man," and I found that astounding, because the phrase I grew up with wasn't "I am a man," it was "I am the man," and I was amazed at how it went from this collective statement during segregation to this seemingly selfish statement after integration. And I wanted to ponder that, so I decided to remix that text in as many ways as I could think of, and I like to think of the top line as a timeline of American history, and the last line as a poem, and it says, "I am the man. Who's the man. You the man. What a man. I am man. I am many. I am, am I. I am, I am. I am, Amen. DW: Wow, so fascinating. (Applause) But what we learn from this experience is the most powerful two words in the English language is, "I am." And we each have the capacity to love. Thank you. (Applause)
La verdad siempre está en manos del real creador de imágenes y depende de nosotros considerar realmente lo que se recorta. Pensé que podría usar su investigación como un punto de partida de las cosas que veía en la sociedad y quería pensar cómo usar imágenes históricas para hablar sobre el pasado presente y pensar cómo hablar sobre la perenne lucha por los derechos humanos y la igualdad de derechos a través de mi apropiación de fotografías en forma de escultura, video, instalación y pinturas. A pesar de todo, una pieza me ha afectado sobremanera y continúa inspirándome. Se basa en esta fotografía de Ernest Withers, que tomó esta foto en 1968 en la Marcha de Trabajadores de Saneamiento de Memphis de hombres y mujeres de pie colectivamente para afirmar su humanidad. Tenían carteles que decían "soy un hombre" y encontré eso asombroso, porque la frase con la que crecí no era "Yo soy un hombre", era "Yo soy el hombre" y me sorprendió cómo pasó de esa afirmación colectiva durante la segregación a esta afirmación aparentemente egoísta tras la integración. Y quería reflexionar sobre eso, y decidí volver a mezclar ese texto de tantas maneras como posibles, y me gusta pensar en la línea superior como una línea de tiempo de la historia estadounidense, y la última línea como un poema, y dice, "Yo soy el hombre. Quién es el hombre. Tú el hombre. Qué hombre. Yo soy hombre. Yo soy muchos. Yo soy, soy yo Yo soy, yo soy. Soy un hombre. DW: Guau, tan fascinante. (Aplausos) Pero lo que aprendemos de esta experiencia es la dos palabras más poderosas en el idioma inglés es "Yo soy". Y cada uno tenemos la capacidad de amar. Gracias. (Aplausos)